Back in the 10th year of Yuankang
元康十年の頃
Our Xuan Kingdom's annual tax revenue
我が大宣国の一年間の税収
Could reach over 18 million taels
1800万両余りに達することができる
Why, when it reached Chancellor Xie
なぜ謝の手に渡るのか
Only 10.5 million taels remained?
残りは1050万両しかありません
I
しん
Deserve death ten thousand times
私は千の死を遂げます
Your Majesty
陛下
After several major battles in recent years
数年前にいくつかの大きな戦いを戦った
Border trade with the Wuzhao was closed
国境とウーウーとの交易は閉鎖されました
This
これ
Lost a large amount of revenue
これは大きな収入の損失です
Your Majesty
陛下あなた
Implemented benevolent policies for the people
民に仁政を施す
Taxes everywhere were reduced, this
各地の税はすべて多少減免されている
Lost another large amount of revenue
これでまた大きな収入が減ってしまった
Your Majesty
陛下
For Your Majesty's grand ambitions
陛下の偉大な志のために
I will definitely find a way
私は必ず方法を考え出します
To quickly fill the treasury
できるだけ早く国庫を潤す
Physicians often say
医者の常言
Severe illness requires strong medicine
重い病には強い薬を用いるべきだ
If there is any blame
ただし非難の名は臣に由来する
I will bear it
来てくれる
Alright, alright
はいはい
I'm tired
私は疲れた
Think it over yourself
自分を磨きなさい
All withdraw
みんな下がってください
Yes
はい
I take my leave
臣退出を告げます
Come out
できてください
Your Majesty
陛下
I have verified everything
事件はすでに全て確認済みです
The Xie family colluded with factions
謝家は仲間と結託した
Layered exploitation of state taxes
国家税負を重ねて搾り取る
Originally two hundred taels of silver
元々二百両の銀
When it reached the court
朝廷の手に渡った
Only one hundred taels remained
残りはわずか百両だけだ
Also
まだ
This year's Ministry of Revenue's list of official appointments
今年戸部が提出した官員推薦リスト
More than half are Chen clan members
中には大部分が陳氏の親族です
The remaining half
残り半分
Most are also from the Xie and Zu families
大多数も謝家の本家です
And their retainers and students
そして彼らの門人や弟子たち
As for
〜については
The mad horse at the hunting ground
以前狩猟場で
That nearly collided with Your Majesty
陛下に突進しかけたあの狂った馬
I
しん
Also heard some rumors
ちょっとした噂も聞いたことがあります
Saying
言う
According to informants
情報提供者によると
Because the Wuzhao are skilled with horses
邬伖人は良い馬を持っているので
So in General Zu Yue's army
だから祖月祖将軍の軍の中で
They once developed a kind of
かつて開発したことがある一種の
Fierce drug that can make warhorses go mad
戦馬を狂わせる強烈な薬
Your Majesty
陛下
Be careful
気をつけて
And that mad horse that nearly collided with Your Majesty
そしてあの日陛下に突進した狂った馬
Was exactly given this drug
まさにこの薬を使ったのです
The informant also said
情報提供者はさらに言った
That drugged horse
薬を盛られたあの馬
Why are you beating around the bush?
回りくどいことを言っているのか
I told you to speak, so speak
言えと言ったら言う
That horse
あの馬
Was originally meant for the second prince
本来は二殿下に残すはずでした
Only
ただ
The crown prince happened to ride it
ちょうど皇太子が乗って行ってしまった
Enough
いいよ
Keep this matter buried in your stomach
このことはあなたの胸の内にしまっておいて
Understand?
わかりますか
I understand
臣は理解しました
Dismissed
行きなさい
Chancellor Xie Jian'an
謝建安という宰相
Really got his money's worth
本当に値打ちがあるね
Now
今
We are not yet firmly established
私たちはまだ足場が固まっていない
It's not yet time to move against them
まだ彼らに手を出す時ではない
I have a word of warning for you
朕はあなたに一言申し上げたい
Don't trust and rely too much on your subordinates
門下にあまり信頼したり依存したりしないでください
Don't become their puppet
彼らの傀儡になってはいけない
You and your elder brother are family
あなたとあなたのお兄さんこそが家族です
Father really had it difficult back then
父上あの時は本当に大変だったんですね
You lamented the great families growing powerful
あなたは名家が成功することに感嘆しています
Restraining you everywhere
あなたの自由をあらゆる面で制限する
But now
でも今は
The state still has many matters
国家にはまだ多くの事柄があります
That require these people to handle
これらの人々にこれをしてもらう必要があります
Yet you cannot move against them
あなたはあえて彼らを動けなくしてしまう
Now the Chen and Xie families
目下陳家と謝家
Frequently intermarry
頻繁に結婚する
If they unite
彼らは団結した
Will only become harder to deal with
ますます対処しにくくなるばかりだ
Reform is necessary
改革を行わなければならない
But reform
改造可能
How should it be done?
どう直せばいいですか
Treatise on Land
土地十論
Sheng'er's political ideas are very good
盛児の政治論の考えはとても良いです
Can indeed solve Xuan's current
確かに宣国の現在の状況を解決することができる
Contradictions and problems
矛盾と問題
But some ideas are still too one-sided
しかしいくつかの考えはやはり偏っている
To successfully implement it
成功を収めて実行するには
We need someone with a high enough position
まだ十分に高い位置が必要です
And
それに
Who can put the state's interests first
国家の利益を最優先に置くことができる
And is absolutely trustworthy
また絶対に信頼できる人
Marquis of Yongning
永寧侯
Xie Xuan
謝玄